<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>statistics on Is this Math?</title>
    <link>/categories/statistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in statistics on Is this Math?</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Axiomatically, the frequentist likelihood is invariant under parameter transformation</title>
      <link>/2020/07/27/axiomatically-the-frequentist-likelihood-is-invariant-under-parameter-transformation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/27/axiomatically-the-frequentist-likelihood-is-invariant-under-parameter-transformation/</guid>
      <description>Axiomatically, the frequentist likelihood is invariant under parameter transformationThat our inference be invariant under 1-1 data transformation seems like a natural requirement and follows from the definition of the likelihood. That is if we transform the data, we transform the pdf and thus have a new likelihood.
It seems reasonable to require that the likelihood ratio be invariant under fixed parameter transformation as well: regardless if I estimate \(\sigma^2\) or \(\sigma\) I should have the same amount of information.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transforming the data of a likelihood involves a Jacobian; why the likelihood ratio is the key object</title>
      <link>/2020/07/27/transforming-the-data-of-a-likelihood-involves-a-jacobian/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/27/transforming-the-data-of-a-likelihood-involves-a-jacobian/</guid>
      <description>The likelihood ratio is the primary object of interest because if we transform the data \(X\) to \(Y\), our information about a fixed parameter \(\theta\) should not change. This mathematically follows from calculus.
Transforming the data (random variable) of a likelihood involves a Jacobian term\[L(\theta; y) = L(\theta; x)\left| \frac{\partial x}{\partial y}\right|\]
The [[Classical definition of the likelihood]] starts with a statistical model and thus a probability density \(p_\theta(x)\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model-assisted frameworks: a hybrid between design-based and model-based frameworks</title>
      <link>/2020/07/21/model-assisted-frameworks-a-hybrid-between-design-based-and-model-based-frameworks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/21/model-assisted-frameworks-a-hybrid-between-design-based-and-model-based-frameworks/</guid>
      <description>To overcome the limitations of both the pure model-based and pure design-based frameworks, a hybrid model-assisted framework has been developed. In this framework a statistical model is specified to determine the parameters of interest but estimation and inference of said parameters is done under a design-based framework.
For example consider a model fit on the finite population of size \(N\) as
\[y_i = \beta_0 + \beta_1x_i\]
then the finite population quantity of interest are \(\beta_0\) and \(\beta_1\) values that minimizes that squared error:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Design-based vs Model-based framework</title>
      <link>/2020/07/20/design-based-vs-model-based-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/20/design-based-vs-model-based-framework/</guid>
      <description>The postulate of randomness thus resolves itself into the question, “Of what population is this a random sample?” which must frequently be asked by every practical statistician. (Fisher 1922)
When we say our sample set is a sample from a population, what population are we talking about?
In Fisher’s model-based framework, you begin with specifying a statistical model which specifies a data generating process for your \(y_i\)’s. Now imagine we generate and store \(y_i\)’s ad infinitum.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>